Felipe Hinojosa collection of interviews with Latino Mennonites
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
Felipe Hinojosa collection of interviews with Latino Mennonites 2003-2009
AFC 2016/042
Hinojosa, Felipe, 1977-
44 items.
2 linear feet.
44 sound cassettes: analog.
Archive of Folk Culture, American Folklife Center, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Collection of field recordings of approximately 85 hours of oral history interviews with about 20 Latino Mennonites in South Texas, Puerto Rico, Kansas, and Indiana. Topics of the interviews include religious and ethnic community formation; the politics of cultural, religious, and ethnic identity; civil rights and social justice; and interactions between evangelical and mainstream religious groups.
Provenance
Felipe Hinojosa; Donation; 2016.
Access and Restrictions
The Felipe Hinojosa collection of interviews with Latino Mennonites is open to research. To request materials, please contact the Folklife Reading Room at https://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/folklife.contact
Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Bibliography
Published in: Hinojosa, Felipe. Latino Mennonites: Civil Rights, Faith, and Evangelical Culture (Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 2014)
Biographical Note
Dr. Felipe Hinojosa is an Associate Professor of History at Texas A&M University. His interests include Latina/o and Mexican American studies, American religion, social movements, gender, and comparative race and ethnicity. His publications include, Latino Mennonites: Civil Rights, Faith, and Evangelical Culture (2014) and Apostles of Change: Latino Radical Politics, Church Occupations, and the Fight to Save the Barrio (2021).
Hinojosa was born in the border town of Brownsville, Texas. He grew up as a Mennonite in the church his parents founded in South Texas. Throughout his upbringing as a Mexican American evangélico, Hinojosa was faced with questions not only about his own religion but also about broader issues of Latino evangelicalism, identity, and civil rights politics. In the late 1990s, Hinojosa met Neftali Torres, a Puerto Rican Mennonite pastor, at a gathering of Mexican Mennonite pastors. At the gathering, Torres discussed the Minority Ministries Council (MMC), a small multi-ethnic group of Latino and African American Mennonites, who operated in the Mennonite Church from 1968 to 1973. Hinojosa became interested in the narrative of black and brown Mennonites who worked to open the doors of the church to minorities. For the next 15 years, Hinojosa began to reconstruct the history through a series of oral histories in South Texas, Puerto Rico, Kansas, and Indiana, and Chicago.
Hinojosa received his PhD in history from the University of Houston in 2009, MA in history from the University of Texas Rio Grande Valley (2004), and a BA in English from Fresno Pacific University (1999). In 2015 he won the Américo Paredes Book Award by the Center for Mexican American Studies at South Texas College.
Scope and Content
The collection documents 15 years of research Felipe Hinojosa's conducted within the community of the Latino Mennonites from South Texas, Puerto Rico, Kansas, and Indiana. The oral histories which were conducted between 2003-2009, consists of 22 interviews including Neftali Torres, the pastor who inspired Hinojosa to trace the history of the Latino Mennonite Church. The interviews culminated in his book, Latino Mennonites: Civil Rights, Faith, and Evangelical Culture (2014). These oral histories document the forgotten history of the Mennonites and tell the story of the preachers who turned social justice advocates transforming the Mennonite Church from the grassroots. In his book, Hinojosa traces the Latino presence within the Mennonite Church, from the origins of Mennonite missions in Latino communities to the conflicted relationship between the Mennonite Church, the California farmworker movements, and the rise of Latino evangelical politics in the United States. He also analyzed how the politics of the Chicano, Puerto Rican, and black freedom struggles of the 1960s and 1970s civil rights movements captured the imagination of Mennonite leaders who belonged to a church known more for rural and peaceful agrarian life than for social protest.
Arrangement
The Felipe Hinojosa collection of interviews with Latino Mennonites has one series: 1. Interviews with Latino Mennonites, circa 2003-2009.
The interviews are arranged alphabetically by the interviewee’s last name.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Hinojosa, Felipe, 1977-
Subjects
Hispanic American Mennonites--Civil rights--Religious aspects.; Hispanic American Mennonites--History--20th century.; Hispanic American Mennonites--Indiana.; Hispanic American Mennonites--Interviews.; Hispanic American Mennonites--Kansas.; Hispanic American Mennonites--Puerto Rico.; Hispanic American Mennonites--Texas.; Hispanic Americans--Civil rights.; Hispanic Americans--Social conditions.; Race relations--Religious aspects--Mennonites.
Places
Middle West, event place.; Puerto Rico, event place.; Texas, event place.
Form/Genre
Field recordings.; Interviews.; Oral histories.; Sound recordings.
Container List
- Series 1: Interviews with Latino Mennonites, circa 2003-2009
  - Ted Chapa, tapes 1-2, January 22, 2007, AFC 2016/042: SR01 - SR02; 2 sound cassettes, 90 min.
  - Paul Conrad and Ann Conrad, tapes 1-3, April 21, 2007, AFC 2016/042: SR03 - SR05; 3 sound cassettes, 90 min.
    New Carlisle, Ohio. Possibly recorded on another date.
  - Lupe DeLeón, tapes 1-2, AFC 2016/042: SR06 - SR10; 5 sound cassettes, 90 min.
  - Seferina DeLeón, tapes 1-2, April 21, 2007, AFC 2016/042: SR11 - SR12; 2 sound cassettes, 90 min.
    Goshen, Indiana
  - Ruperto "Tito" Guedea, May 3, 2007, AFC 2016/042: SR13; 1 sound cassette, 90 min.
  - Samuel Hernandez, AFC 2016/042: SR14; 1 sound cassette, 60 min.
  - Jose Enrique Jimenez, AFC 2016/042: SR15; 1 sound cassette, 90 min.
  - Hector Lugo, AFC 2016/042: SR16; 1 sound cassette, 90 min.
    Puerto Rico
  - Rolando Mireles, September 16-17, 2003, AFC 2016/042: SR17; 1 sound cassette, 90 min.
  - Rolando Mireles, February 10, 2004, AFC 2016/042: SR18; 1 sound cassette, 90 min.
  - Jesus "Chuy" Navarro, tapes 1-2, January 21, 2007, AFC 2016/042: SR19 - SR20; 2 sound cassettes, 90 min.
    Robstown, Texas
  - Enrique Ortiz, AFC 2016/042: SR21; 1 sound cassette, 90 min.
  - Jose Ortiz, tapes 1-2, AFC 2016/042: SR22 - SR23; 1 sound cassette, 60 min.; 1 sound cassette, 90 min.
  - Ricardo Peña, tapes 1-2, July 15, 2003, AFC 2016/042: SR24 - SR25; 2 sound cassettes, 90 min.
  - Ricardo Peña, August 14, 2003, AFC 2016/042: SR26; 1 sound cassette, 90 min.
  - Ricardo Peña; Yolanda Villareal, January 8, 2004, AFC 2016/042: SR27; 1 sound cassette, 90 min.
  - Yolanda Villareal, January 8, 2004, AFC 2016/042: SR28; 1 sound cassette, 90 min.
  - John Powell, tapes 1-4, April 26, 2007, AFC 2016/042: SR29 - SR32; 4 sound cassettes, 90 min.
  - Alfredo Tagle, tapes 1-2, September 4, 2003, AFC 2016/042: SR33 - SR34; 2 sound cassettes, 90 min.
  - Gracie Torres, June 20, 2007, AFC 2016/042: SR35; 1 sound cassette, 90 min.
    Lourdes Café, Puerto Rico.
  - Neftali Torres, tapes 1-4, undated, AFC 2016/042: SR36 - SR39; 4 sound cassettes, 90 min.
  - Rosario Vallejo and Perfecta DeLeón, tapes 1-2, December 28, 2006, AFC 2016/042: SR40 - SR41; 2 sound cassettes, 60 min.
    Rosario's home in Mathis, Texas.
  - Rosario Vallejo, February, AFC 2016/042: SR42; 1 sound cassette, 90 min.
    Rosario's home in Mathis, Texas. Possibly recorded in 2007.
  - John Ventura, tapes 1-2, September 14, 2009, AFC 2016/042: SR43 - SR44; 2 sound cassettes, 90 min.